<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Handy Tools | thought|pipe]]></title>
  <link href="http://elauqsap.github.io/blog/categories/handy-tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://elauqsap.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-30T00:21:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://elauqsap.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[elauqsap]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[3lauqsap@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why You Should Get Pocket]]></title>
    <link href="http://elauqsap.github.io/blog/2015/02/15/why-you-should-get-pocket/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T19:28:23-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://elauqsap.github.io/blog/2015/02/15/why-you-should-get-pocket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever I set up a new device the first thing I download onto it is <a href="https://getpocket.com">Pocket</a>. This app is seriously handy for tech people and adding it to Flipboard just takes it to another level. My primary use for Pocket is to help me keep up with the technology scene. The landscape changes on a daily basis, there is always some new trending language, an update to some framework or some cool device. Normally each day during some down time, I will flip through my feeds and skim through articles that catch my eye. Sometimes I can&rsquo;t finish the article, sometimes it is a tutorial for something I want to do, and other times it&rsquo;s something I might want to share. With Pocket, a simple click of a button solves all of this and more. You can store, share, tag, synchronize and much more.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Probably the best feature of pocket is the offline storage and tagging. I use this in my development workflow to store and index tutorials relating to my current project. Some of you may not have this problem, but browser tab hoarding is a real issue for me. So when I find something beneficial instead of leaving it up in a tab the entire time I save it to pocket and tag it for later use. No more shooting myself in the foot searching my browsing history for the site. Anyways, I just wanted to share this nifty app and how it has saved me hours of my time. If you are not already using Pocket and you are in technology, do yourself a favor and get it today.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
